## Zaman Rahimi Python Engineer

## **Summary**

Highly motivated, self-driven Software/Python engineer with years of extensive experience in the area of Software Development, APIs testing and development, software deployment, containerization, container orchestration, configuration management, infrastructure as code (IaC), CI/CD within Software, Data, Cloud and DevOps context. Hands-on with Python, Django, REST APIs and Django Rest Framework, FastAPI, Data analytics & Cleaning, Scripting, Terraform, Kubernetes, Jenkins, Ansible and AWS. Self-starter and management skills to effectively communicate with peers and address business needs. Have proven record of handling challenges, meeting business needs, and delivering business solutions without sacrificing quality and agility.

## **Work Experience**

#### Python Engineer | Energy Transfer

July 2023 - Current

- Developed data center infrastructure management system with Python/Django, including back-end components, REST APIs, and user interfaces.
- Designed and implemented RESTful APIs with Python/Django Rest Framework to facilitate data exchange among different business applications such as NetBox, Gluware, Solarwinds and more.
- Integrated and synchronized data across multiple applications through REST APIs, optimizing data transfer performance, security and accuracy.
- Developed and deployed Python scripts for automating data processing tasks, including data collection, cleaning, analysis, manipulation and testing.
- Created and maintained Continuous Integration/Continuous Deployment (CI/CD) pipelines, ensuring smooth deployment and release processes.
- Collaborated with cross-functional teams to collect requirements, conducted code reviews, and provided technical expertise.
- Developed python scripts to format coding style based on python enhancement proposal (PEP8) and performed quality analysis and security standards on the codes.
- Debugged software applications, identifying and resolving issues to ensure optimal performance.
- Stayed up-to-date with industry best practices and emerging technologies to enhance development processes and outcomes.

### DevOps/Python Engineer | Tetra Tech

January 2020 - July 2023

#### zaman.rahimi.rz@gmail.com

#### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

#### 1. Languages & Frameworks:

- ✓ Python
- ✓ Django
- ✓ Django REST Framework
- ✓ ReactJS
- ✓ HTML & CSS
- ✓ Bootstrap
- ✓ Database
- **✓ FastAPI**
- ✓ GraphQL

#### 2. Python libraries & Modules:

- ✓ Django / REST Framework
- ✓ Pandas
- ✓ Requests
- ✓ Matplotlib
- ✓ Seaborn
- ✓ Black & Autopep8
- ✓ Beautiful Soap

#### 3. Cloud & DevOps Stacks:

- ✓ AWS
- ✓ GCP
- ✓ Azure DevOps
- ✓ Terraform
- ✓ Ansible
- ✓ Docker
- ✓ Kubernetes
- √ CI/CD (Jenkins)
- ✓ Linux
- ✓ Git
- ✓ Github, Gitlab

#### 4. AWS Services:

- ✓ IAM
- ✓ EC2
- ✓ RDS
- ✓ ECS
- ✓ VPC
- ✓ Load balancer

- Accelerated software development lifecycle by designing and implementing a seamless CI/CD pipeline with Azure DevOps, ensuring continuous integration, testing, and deployment using Python and YAML scripts.
- Achieved remarkable application security, reliability, and accessibility by architecting and managing AWS infrastructure, including EC2 instances, VPCs, subnets, security groups, NACLs, auto-scaling groups, and load balancers.
- Increased operational efficiency by automating repetitive tasks, such as scheduled backups, using Python scripting.
- Provisioned AWS resources using Terraform with IaC best practices to ensure consistency across the board and better tracking of resources.
- Orchestrated and managed containerized applications on AWS EKS for high availability, scalability, and performance.
- Ensured application quality, security, and compliance through integrating a comprehensive suite of testing methodologies, including performance, integration, unit, system, security, usability, and compatibility testing within the CI/CD process.

# Software Developer | DAI | Dec 2018 – Jan 2020

- Assisted in containerization of applications using Docker and worked with DevOps team for streamlining local development using Docker containers.
- Assisted writing Jenkins pipelines for apps deployed to Kubernetes environment while coordinating with cross-functional teams to improve release cycles and automating build, test, and deployment processes.
- Designed, developed, and maintained responsive, user-friendly websites using Python, Django, HTML, CSS, and JavaScript, resulting in increased user engagement and satisfaction.
- Leveraged Django's built-in features, such as the ORM and template system, to create dynamic, data-driven web applications with efficient database interactions.
- Enhanced applications by adding new features based on client's need and requirements

Software Engineer	FHI360	March 2015 – Dec 2018

- Developed and maintained robust web applications using Python/Django, resulting notable increase in site performance and user satisfaction.
- Collaborated with cross-functional teams to deliver high-quality software solutions, utilizing agile methodologies to ensure timely project completion.
- Conducted code reviews and provided constructive feedback to peers, fostering a culture of continuous improvement and best practices in software development.
- Mentored junior software engineers, providing guidance on PHP and Drupal best practices to enhance team skills and knowledge.

#### **PROJECTS**

- Developed and implemented infrastructure management system with Django, Django Rest Framework (DRF) and ReactJS.
- ✓ Created CICD with Azure

  DevOps, Python and YAML to automate and sync data processing and analyzing among different applications such NetBox, Gluware,

  Solarwinds and F5Sellverline.
- Created Python scripts to populate pull and populate data into the related applications such as NetBox DCIM and IPAM.
- Deployed a web application to EKS using a CI/CD pipeline
- ✓ Created and maintained CI/CD pipeline using Jenkins and GitHub.
- ✓ Implemented On-Premises database replica to increase High Availability and Disaster Recovery (HADR)
- ✓ Provisioned AWS resources such as IAM entities, VPC,
   Security Group, EC2, Load
   Balancer, RDS, S3, Route 53
   by Terraform.
- Provisioned and configured
   AWS VPC (Subnet, Internet
   Gateway, NAT Gateway,
   Routing Table) in AWS
- Automated repetitive tasks such as taking backup, code push, automated software deployment and testing.
- Provided security plan on how to keep applications and servers secure.

#### **EDUCATION**

- Master 's in Software Engineering 2017 – 2019 – Bakhtar University
- Bachelor in Computer Science
   2010 2013 Kabul University